fiber it helps you
poop were those not the details that
you've never heard well all right it
turns out fiber probably does more than
just impact your bathroom habits in fact
across multiple analyses including up to
83 studies fiber may have an effect on
the old ticker by affecting your blood
pressure but before we get into the
clinical data it's always nice to brush
up on how fibers proposed to impose its
blood pressure effects and then we'll
discuss why some data indicate fiber
does not have an effect yet other data
indicates that it does have an effect
the great fiber
conspiracy fiber which is a weekly
digested carbohydrate found in plants
translates into proposed blood pressure
reducing effects through its effects on
our
microbiome a grouping of trillions of
microorganisms like bacteria that are
found on and in your body more
specifically fiber is known to affect
the gut microbiome found in your
intestines fiber is known to be
biogenic which if you're anything like
me you find that word completely
uninformative it means that the fiber
promotes the growth of bifido bacteria a
bacterium linked to positive Health
outcomes more specifically fiber can be
taken up by these microbes and converted
into short chain fats so small fat
molecules these short chain fats like
butyrate are expelled from the microbe
and absorbed by the intestinal wall
cells called colonocytes once absorbed
short chain fats can bind receptors
found on the endothelial cells of the
blood vessels these are the cells that
line your blood vessels and control
blood pressure these cells secrete
different molecules that influence
nearby cells known as smooth muscle
cells to contract or relax the
relaxation of these smooth muscle cells
opens the blood vessel thereby reducing
blood pressure now short chain fats
derived from fiber bind to receptors on
endothelial cells and convince them to
secrete blood vessel relaxing molecules
like nitric oxide in that way it's
believed fiber reduces our blood
pressure but I should mention that there
are many other mechanisms Beyond this
one that have been proposed like the
effect that short chain fats have on
insulin resistance which also affects
blood pressure indirectly or short chain
fats also encourage the production of
glucagon like peptide from the
intestinal cells this glucagon like
peptide or gp1 can also influence blood
pressure by binding the kidneys the
heart the blood vessels there's much
more but what I've described is
introduced in this analysis I'd be happy
to do a deeper dive into the various
mechanisms of fiber if you're interested
for now let's move on to some of the
nuances of the clinical data because
there are some nuances to be had I say
this all the time but we can't rely on
mechanistic studies to speak to the true
effect of something for that we need to
rely on human trials so do the human
trials corroborate the mechanisms that
we discussed do they show a blood
pressure lowering effect well yes and no
some do and some don't for example this
analysis including many random control
trials indicates fiber supplementation
is ineffective at reducing certain blood
pressure we can see that here the
studies on the left side and the study
results are on the right the black
Square indicates the average effect of
fiber supplementation versus placebo or
nonfiber inert substance the dotted line
above zero indicates a no effect of
fiber supplementation so if the studies
fall to the left there is a reduction in
blood pressure from fiber consumption
the overall Diamond at the bottom is an
easy way of pulling all the studies into
one illustration overall while the
diamond seems to be moving left in favor
of blood pressure lowering effects the
statistics indicate otherwise there's no
detected effect now interestingly
another analysis shows the same results
it's a similar idea with the pulled
estimate at the bottom indicating no
effect although it looks like it leans
to the left so why are there so many
mechanisms indicating fiber should
provide a blood pressure lowering effect
yet two separate analyses indicate
otherwise well there's several reasons
have you ever experienced frustration
because 10 years ago researchers said
one thing and sometime in the future
they say something completely different
maybe even in the opposite of what they
said for this is a perfect
example both the analyses that I showed
you are from
205 and while comforting that they agree
almost to a te they suffer from a few
issues and I'll get into some of the
others in a bit but the main one is that
they include 24 and 25 randomized
control trials that is a lot of studies
but just because we perceive something
as being a lot doesn't mean that it
actually is sufficient data to detect an
effect if there were one at the
beginning I promised you 83 studies way
more than what we've have here with 83
studies like in this analysis which was
published almost 20 years later and more
studies were published between 2005 and
this analysis indicates fiber does
reduce blood pressure we can see that
here now I'm not going to bog this down
by describing each element of this table
just know that by either way of
analyzing the data a strict pairwise
comparison or a dose response
relationship blood pressure is reduced
with fiber exposure as indicated by the
minus numbers under the mean difference
MD label on the top oh also I realized I
said 83 studies and for those that have
some statistics background you'll note
the studies label there indicates 94 and
93 studies that's referring to the study
arms not the number of studies exactly a
conversation for another day anyway the
point being that once you add much more
data to the analysis even what seems to
be a robust analysis back in 2005 we
gain more clarity on the truth and we
detect and effect where there might be
one something that we couldn't do in
2005 but if I'm honest with you this
analysis from 2005 did show a blood
pressure lowering effect when looking at
diastolic blood pressure here same rules
apply and we see the overall effects
Diamond moves squarely to the left
indicating a reduction so the previous
data that I showed you was in systolic
blood pressure the top number on your
blood pressure reading and these data
are diastolic blood pressure the bottom
number both are important and this is
also corroborated in the other 2005
analysis okay so the takeaways here is
that fiber does reduce blood pressure
pressure but there's still more to say
because there's some key things that
change how we look at this blood
pressure lowering effect in fact fibers
of blood pressure reduction effect may
be conditional I say that because if we
pop open these analyses again and we
look at the blood pressure lowering
effects of fiber more closely here we
see that the benefits are outsized for
one group of people and just about
non-existent for another those two
groups are the people most affected
people with high or normal blood
pressure as we can see by the data the
darker bars are the people with
hypertension so high blood pressure and
if the bars go down from the Baseline of
zero that indicates a blood pressure
lowering effect clearly only those with
hypertension experience a blood pressure
reducing effect from fiber consumption
both other analyses indicate similar
results so does that mean that people
who don't have high blood pressure can
just kick fiber out of their diet well
if you're only concerned about blood
pressure it's true that fiber may not
offer much for you however that assumes
that fiber doesn't provide any other
health benefits which is an incorrect
assumption however we can say that
people who have high blood pressure
should consider working on their fiber
intake especially okay how much fiber
and what are some sources of fiber we'll
get into that but there's much more to
this story than I can cover in this
version of the video I say this version
because there's an extended version of
this video that you're watching which
covers more on the most effective fibers
if more fibers necessarily better
differences in types of fiber and some
additional nuances on dosing sourcing
and more all of that is included with
the physionic Insiders along with access
to all my work my research reviews
Insider podcasts and more and written
summaries of all The Insider videos
anyway if you're interested in the full
video consider joining the Insiders it's
linked in the description now what are
good sources and how much to consume in
a non-exhaustive list raspberries
blackberries artichokes peas oats black
beans lentils chia seeds avocados are a
few Foods although there are plenty of
others these will also allow you to
fulfill the total amounts needed per day
on that front amount needed there's a
few different recommendations but the
general recommendation is around 25 to
40 grams of fiber per day on the lower
end for women according to this analysis
I'd argue the first 20 gram are the most
impactful from a blood pressure
standpoint for more exact intake the
numbers are based on per 1,000 calorie
basis around 14 G of fiber per 1,000
calories consume per day if you know the
amount that you consume per day at least
precisely so overall what's the short
and suweet of it fiber has a mild blood
pressure lowering effect although the
effect size is small to negligable if
you don't have high blood pressure if
you do the impact of fibers increase
pretty substantially around 3 to Five
Point drop in blood pressure the biggest
bang for your buck is in the first 20
grams of consumption although
recommendations reach higher than that
around 14 G per 1,000 calories consumed
per day and if you're concerned about
heart health I have plenty more publicly
available material right here thanks for
tuning in